# Sushovan Majhi

Postdoctoral Research Fellow, School of Information, University of California, Berkeley, USA smajhi@berkeley.edu | +1-504-616-3661 | Homepage | GitHub | LinkedIn

### RESEARCH INTERESTS

Topological data analysis (TDA), applied algebraic topology, computational topology, computational geometry, road-map reconstruction from GPS trajectory data.

My research primarily focuses on **shape reconstruction** and **big data analysis**. More specifically, I am interested in solving real-world problems using tools from **algebraic topology** and **geometry**. In order to analyze large, complex, and noisy data, I develop provable and efficient techniques to find and classify significant geometric and topological features.

### **TEACHING INTERESTS**

- UNDERGRADUATE: Calculus, statistics, probability theory, data science, real analysis, topology, linear algebra, differential geometry, algorithms and data structures, computational geometry.
- **GRADUATE:** Analysis, algebraic topology, manifold theory, algorithms, computational complexity, computational geometry.

### WORK EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Research Fellow in Data Science
School of Information, University of California, Berkeley, USA

January 2021-current

• Lecturer (MIDS Program)

August 2020-December 2020

School of Information, University of California, Berkeley, USA

*Role*: The position offered me (off-campus) work experience during my doctoral studies, and has served as a Curricular Practical Training (CPT).

#### **EDUCATION**

Doctor of Philosophy in Mathematics
Tulane University, New Orleans, LA, USA.

August 2014-December 2020

Advisor: Prof. Carola Wenk

*Courses*: computational geometry, computational topology, topological data analysis, differential geometry, differentiable manifolds, algorithms, data structures, computational complexity, applied mathematics, scientific computing.

• Master of Science in Mathematics

August 2009-May 2012

Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Bangalore, India

*Courses:* ordinary and partial differential equations, probability theory, complex analysis, functional analysis, numerical linear algebra, measure theory, mechanics.

• Bachelor of Science in Mathematics (Hons.)

July 2006-May 2009

Ramakrishna Mission Vidyamandira, Calcutta University, West Bengal, India

Courses: calculus, real analysis, linear algebra, numerical analysis, game theory, and statistics.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

• Computation of Gromov-Hausdorff Distance in Euclidean Space

April 2019-current

Collaborators: Helmut Alt, Jeffrey Vitter, and Carola Wenk

We investigate the computational aspects of Gromov-Hausdorff distance between sets equipped with the Euclidean metric. We used the Hausdorff distance under isometry to develop an approximation algorithm for Gromov-Hausdorff distance on the real line with a tight approximation factor of  $(1 + \frac{1}{4})$ .

### • Discrete Morse Theory in Graph Reconstruction

Collaborators: Brittany Fasy and Carola Wenk

We propose a threshold-based framework to obtain both topologically and geometrically faithful reconstruction of planar metric graphs from (noisy) spatial data. We make use of topological ideas, like discrete Morse theory and persistence homology and statistical ideas like kernel density estimation (KDE) to capture statistically significant features.

# • Topological Reconstruction of Geodesic Spaces

December 2016-May 2019

October 2018-current

Collaborator: Brittany Fasy and Rafal Komendarczyk

Role: Research Assistant

PI: Carola Wenk

We investigate the reconstruction of geodesic subspaces of Euclidean spaces using the Vietoris-Rips and Čech complexes from a dense sample around it. We propose two new sampling parameters: **distortion** of embedding and **convexity radius** of the underlying geodesic space. We guarantee a successful computation of the Betti numbers. For the special case of a planar metric graphs, we also develop an algorithm for its geometric reconstruction.

# Dynamics and Prognosis of Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia (CML)

August 2012-November 2013

National Center for Biological Sciences, TIFR, Bangalore, India

Role: Junior Research Fellow

PI: Seema Nanda

In this joint effort to develop better prognostic tools for doctors, computational scientists teamed up with medical officers and biologists to understand the dynamics of CML by modeling the disease by systems of **differential equations**. In our parameter fitting, we made use of the big existing data collected from a large pool of CML patients. We also performed (statistical) **sensitivity analysis** to better understand the parameter spaces for our model.

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- Link Sushovan Majhi, Jeffrey Vitter, and Carola Wenk. Approximating Gromov-Hausdorff Distance in Euclidean Space. *arXiv:1912.13008* [math.MG], 2019
- Link Brittany Terese Fasy, Sushovan Majhi, and Carola Wenk. Threshold-based graph reconstruction using discrete Morse theory. In *Fall Workshop on Computational Geometry*, New York, NY, November 2018
- Link Brittany Terese Fasy, Rafal Komendarczyk, Sushovan Majhi, and Carola Wenk. On the Reconstruction of Geodesic Subspaces of  $\mathbb{R}^n$ . arXiv:1810.10144 [math.AT], 2018, Submitted to JoCG (Journal of Computational Geometry)
- Link Brittany Terese Fasy, Rafal Komendaczyk, Sushovan Majhi, and Carola Wenk. Topological reconstruction of metric graphs in  $\mathbb{R}^n$ . In *Fall Workshop on Computational Geometry*, New York, NY, October 2017

### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### Statistics for Data Science, MIDS

August 2020-current

School of Information, University of California, Berkeley, USA

The course covers the following topics: probability theory, sampling distributions, estimators and convergence theorems, confidence intervals, hypothesis testing, and regression.

# • Undergraduate Statistics for Business Students

**Summer 2019** 

Tulane University, USA

The course covered the following topics: sampling methods, probability theory, random variables, sampling distribution, confidence intervals, hypothesis testing, and linear regression.

# • Linear Algebra, Complex Analysis

January 2013-June 2013

Christ University and Scimetric Pvt Ltd, Bangalore, India

## • Analysis, Linear Algebra, Complex Analysis

November 2011-July 2012

GATE-IIT Coaching Institute, JP Nagar, Bangalore, India Graduate level, for competitive national exams, e.g., National Eligibility Test

# • Analysis and Linear Algebra

February 2012-July 2012

MES College, Department of Mathematics, Malleswaram, Bangalore, India

### COMPUTATIONAL SKILLS

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES: Java, C, Python, Ruby, JavaScript, SQL, Matlab, Bash.

OTHERS: Databases, Git, Ruby on Rails, REST, AWS, Heroku, Jekyll.

### **SOFTWARE PROJECTS**

### • Shape Reconstruction Visualization

Link | GitHub

To complement my research, I implemented my topological reconstruction algorithm for planar metric graphs in this library. The library is written in JavaScript and made available to users as a web-app. Skills: JavaScript, HTML, CSS.

 Avimukh Link

Avimukh is a Bengali website for poets, writers, and bloggers. I designed its backend in Ruby on Rails framework. The web-app is hosted on Heroku.

Skills: Ruby on Rails, Ruby, SQL, JavaScript, HTML.

### ENTREPRENEURIAL EXPERIENCE

### Scimetric Edulabs Private Limited

December 2012-April 2017

Bangalore, India

Role: co-founder and director

In this start-up venture, our objective was to motivate and train students in higher education. We won franchise to work with several private colleges in India. We coached science students for standardized entrance tests for PhD and academic jobs. The company employed 6 trainers.

### SCHOLARSHIPS AND CERTIFICATES

- UGC-CSIR NET Research Fellowship, India June 2012
- TIFR Junior Research Fellowship

for pursuing Integrated PhD studies at TIFR-CAM, Bangalore, India. August 2009.

 Secured grade "A" in SCIENCE TALENT SEARCH EXAMINATION conducted by JATIYA VIJNAN PARISAD and INDIAN SCIENCE CONGRESS ASSOCIATION

### CONFERENCES AND WORKSHOPS ATTENDED

 NSF-CBMS Conference and Software Day on Topological Methods in Machine Learning and Artificial Intelligence May 13-18, 2019

Department of Mathematics, College of Charleston, South Carolina, USA

• Fall Workshop on Computational Geometry Queens College, New York, USA

October, 2018

• Fall Workshop on Computational Geometry SUNY (Stony Brook), New York, USA

November, 2017

Spring School on Discrete and Computational Geometry

April 17-21, 2017

Simon's Center, Stony Brook, New York, USA

 Topology, Geometry, and Data Analysis Conference at OSU Ohio State University, Columbus, USA

May 16-20, 2016